{"tossups": [{"question": "<em>This author wrote a poem about a man who frames Ralph de Wilton before dying at the Battle</em> <em>of Flodden Field.</em> This man wrote about Jeanie Deans, who seeks a pardon from Queen Caroline after the Porteous Riots. Frederick Douglass borrowed his surname from the work of this author, who included the Templar Brian de Bois-Guilbert, Robin Hood, and Richard the Lionhearted in another novel. For 10 points, name this author of <em>Marmion</em>, <em>The Heart of Midlothian</em>, and <em>Ivanhoe</em>.", "answer": "Sir Walter <b><u>Scott</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "EA"}, {"question": "<em>This man was assassinated by the centurion Cassius Chaerea.</em> This man was played by Malcolm McDowell in a controversial film adaptation of a Gore Vidal novel. He may have executed the Praetorian prefect Macro, who had smothered his predecessor. This third son of Germanicus ordered his men to collect seashells after his invasion of Gaul. For 10 points, name this Roman emperor who succeeded Tiberius and was accused of madness.", "answer": "<b><u>Caligula</u></b> [or <b><u>Gaius</u></b> Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus<b>]</b>  {I}", "metadata": "EA"}, {"question": "<em>Before becoming Ambassador to the UK, the historian George Bancroft was appointed to this</em> <em>post.</em> During the Teapot Dome scandal, Edwin Denby was forced to resign this position. Abel Upshur left this post to become Secretary of State after the resignation of Daniel Webster. Another holder of this cabinet position was nicknamed \u201cNeptune\u201d by Abraham Lincoln and was named Gideon Welles. For 10 points, name this cabinet position responsible for the fleets of the United States.", "answer": "United States <b><u>Secretary of the Navy</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "EA"}, {"question": "<em>Forces of this empire were defeated at the Battle of the Maule by the Mapuche</em>. This empire sacked the city of Chan Chan and conquered the rival Chimu under the leadership of Pachacuti. Record keeping in this empire was accomplished through a system of strings and knots called quipu. The people of this empire worshipped the creator Viracocha and the storm goddess Illapa. For 10 points, name this South American Empire which was centered at Cusco.", "answer": "<b><u>Inca</u></b>n Empire  {I}", "metadata": "EA"}, {"question": "<em>During World War I, this activity was undertaken by those stationed at Room 40.</em> The Polish machine Bomba was designed to do this. This is considered impossible if a one-time pad is used correctly. During World War II, Alan Turing and others stationed at Bletchley Park conducted this task. The results of that work were designated \u201cUltra\u201d and resulted from failures of the Enigma machine. For 10 points, name this task often necessary to reading enemy messages.", "answer": "<b><u>code-breaking</u></b> [or <b><u>cryptography</u></b>; or <b><u>decrypt</u></b>ing; or <b><u>cryptanalysis</u></b>]  {I}", "metadata": "EA"}, {"question": "<em>This justice joined William Brennan in dissenting on every death penalty case after</em> Gregg. After this justice\u2019s 1991 retirement, George H.W. Bush appointed Clarence Thomas to take his spot. As an attorney, he successfully argued <em>Shelley v. Kraemer</em>, which ended restrictive covenants. In another case, this man persuaded the Warren Court to rule unanimously that separate but equal schools were unlawful. For 10 points, name this civil rights lawyer who argued <em>Brown v. Board of Education.</em>", "answer": "Thurgood <b><u>Marshall</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "EA"}, {"question": "<em>This king built the White Tower, which became the Tower of London.</em> This king\u2019s flagship, the <em>Mora</em>, was constructed at Barfleur. After heading off a Danish invasion in support of Edgar the Aetheling, this king launched a subjugation campaign called the Harrying of the North. Late in his reign, he completed a great survey of England called the Domesday (<b>pr. DOOMS-day</b>) Book. For 10 points, name this Duke of Normandy and King of England who won the Battle of Hastings.", "answer": "<b><u>William the Conqueror</u></b> [or <b><u>William I</u></b>; prompt on \u201cWilliam\u201d]  {I}", "metadata": "EA"}, {"question": "<em>Frederick Roth created a sculpture of Balto for this site.</em> Diane Arbus photographed a boy holding a toy hand grenade in this place. A Charles Ives piece is titled for this place \u201cin the dark.\u201d Christo and Jeanne-Claude constructed a series of orange cloth gates in this place. In <em>The</em> <em>Catcher in the Rye</em>, Holden asks where the ducks that live in this place go in the winter. For 10 points, name this place designed by Calvert Vaux and Frederick Law Olmsted, a large park in Manhattan.", "answer": "<b><u>Central Park</u></b> (prompt on Manhattan or New York until the word \u201ctitled\u201d in line 2)  {I}", "metadata": "EA"}, {"question": "<em>This location is the site of the National Memorial Arch</em>. This site was replaced by the area of Jockey Hollow near Morristown. Parson Weems claimed a man named Isaac Potts witnessed a general kneeling in prayer in the snow at this place. It was here that Baron von Steuben introduced new standards of sanitation, logistics, and drilling to the Continental Army. For 10 points, name this Pennsylvania site where Washington spent a harsh winter from 1777 to 1778.", "answer": "<b><u>Valley Forge</u></b> [prompt on \u201cPennsylvania\u201d]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This man directed a biopic about the Dalai Lama titled Kundun.</em> Leonardo DiCaprio builds the Spruce Goose in a biographical film this director made about Howard Hughes titled <em>The Aviator</em>. Daniel Day-Lewis plays Bill \u201cthe Butcher\u201d Cutting, who runs Boss Tweed era New York\u2019s criminal underworld in this director\u2019s <em>Gangs of New York</em>. John Hinckley Jr. was obsessed with this director\u2019s character of Travis Bickle. For 10 points, name this director of <em>Taxi Driver</em>.", "answer": "Martin <b><u>Scorsese</u> </b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {}, {"question": "<em>This city was the site of the Securities Exchange Company founded by Charles Ponzi.</em> On the night of St. Patrick's Day, thirteen artworks were stolen from this city's Gardner Museum. A serial killer in this city strangled women with their own stockings. The Slater-Morrill Shoe Factory in this city's suburb of Braintree was the target of Sacco and Vanzetti's armed robbery.  For 10 points, name this northeastern U.S. city whose police force killed Tamerlan Tsarnaev.", "answer": "<b><u>Boston</u></b>, Massachusetts", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>In this conflict, Conrad III suffered a major loss at the Battle of Dorylaeum</em>. This conflict was provoked by Zengi\u2019s capture of Edessa. During this conflict, Louis VII of France and his wife Eleanor of Aquitaine were ambushed at Laodicea by a Seljuk army. Pope Eugene III asked Bernard of Clairvaux to preach in favor of this conflict, which failed to achieve its main goal. For 10 points, name this 1145-1149 Crusade which saw the Christians fail to conquer Damascus.", "answer": "<b><u>Second Crusade</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>During this battle, Charles Piroth committed suicide</em>. It began with the dropping of paratroopers in Operation Castor and saw the creation of the Beatrice and Gabrielle strongpoints. The losers in this battle utilized the \u201chedgehog\u201d strategy of General Navarre, which failed when opposing artillery was placed in the surrounding hills. It ended with an assault ordered by Vo Nguyen Giap. For 10 points, name this battle where a French garrison was defeated by the Viet Minh.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Dien Bien Phu</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>A political cartoon from this election shows one candidate standing atop two platforms and</em> <em>being pulled in opposite directions by Thomas Watson and Arthur Sewall.</em> The nickname \"Assistant President\" was given to the vice-president elected from it, Garret Hobart. The winning candidate employed Marc Hanna as campaign manager, while his opponent defended bimetallism in his \"Cross of Gold\" speech. For 10 points, name this election that saw William Jennings Bryan defeated by William McKinley.", "answer": "presidential election of <b><u>1896</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>The language of Ilokano is widely spoken only on this island.</em> This island\u2019s Lingayen Gulf was the launching point for a World War II invasion of it. The Bessang Pass and Balete Pass were pitched World War II battles on this island. Daniel Burnham designed this island\u2019s city of Baguio after the Spanish conceded it and its southern partners Palawan and Mindanao to the US after the Spanish American War. For 10 points, name this largest island of the Philippines.", "answer": "<b><u>Luzon</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>During this ruler's tenure, it became popular for women to wear purple or gray dresses to</em> <em>show that they were in \"half-mourning.\"</em> The Kensington system, which educated this leader, was devised by John Conroy to instill weakness. This monarch's country bought a controlling share in the new Suez Canal decades after a marriage to Saxe-Coburg and Gotha's Prince Albert. For 10 points, name this British monarch who celebrated the first Diamond Jubilee in 1897.", "answer": "Queen <b><u>Victoria</u></b> [or Alexandrina <b><u>Victoria</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The issue of LIFE magazine dedicated to this event asked \"How many times must we live</u></b></em> <em><b><u>through these throat-paralyzing sequences of days of gun play, grief, and muffled drums?\"</u> </b></em><b><u>As</u></b> <b><u>photographed by Bill Eppridge, a teenager named Juan Romero shook the hand of this</u></b> <b><u>event's victim just before it occurred in (+)</u>a corridor connecting the kitchen to the Colonial Room in the Ambassador Hotel. This event's victim (*)</b> had just given a speech celebrating his victory in the California primary. For 10 points, name this June 6, 1968 event in which Sirhan Sirhan killed a man who had served as Attorney General under his previously-assassinated brother.", "answer": "<b><u>assassination</u></b> of <b><u>R</u></b>obert Francis \"Bobby\" <b><u>Kennedy</u></b> [or <b><u>assassination</u></b> of <b><u>RFK</u></b>; accept answers with \"Bobby\" in place of \"Robert\"; accept answers containing close synonyms for assassination, prompt on \u201cKennedy assassination\u201d]  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>One composition by this man was used as the national anthem of Biafra</u></b></em><b><u>. This man</u></b> <b><u>referenced the Prelude to</u> </b><em><b><u>Tristan and Isolde</u></b></em><b><u> in the opening of his one-movement Symphony</u></b> <b><u>#7. Robert Kajanus interpreted the Andante of his Symphony #2 in D Major as a (+)</u>\u201cbroken-hearted protest,\u201d and his violin concerto was described by Donald Tovey as a \u201cpolonaise for polar bears.\u201d A nationalist piece by this man was performed under names such as </b><em><b>Impromptu</b></em><b> to evade (*)</b> Russian censors, and he depicted scenes from the Kalevala in tone poems such as <em>The Swan of Tuonela</em>. For 10 points, name this composer of <em>Finlandia</em>.", "answer": "Jean <b><u>Sibelius</u></b>  {I}", "metadata": "CW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Though William Jackson was appointed secretary at this event, notes about its proceedings</u></b></em> <em><b><u>were compiled by Richard Yates.</u></b></em><b><u> At this event, the \u201cCommittee of Detail\u201d was chaired by</u></b> <b><u>\u201cDictator\u201d John Rutledge. Patrick Henry avoided this event because he \u201csmelt a (+)</u> rat.\u201d At this event, which took place one year after a similar gathering in Annapolis, James Wilson proposed the</b> (*) three-fifths compromise and Roger Sherman presented the \u201cConnecticut Compromise.\u201d For 10 points, name this 1787 gathering in Philadelphia to amend the faulty Articles of Confederation.", "answer": "<b><u>Constitutional Convention</u></b> [or <b><u>Philadelphia Convention</u></b> before mentioned; or <b><u>Federal Convention</u></b>; or <b><u>Grand Convention at Philadelphia</u></b> before mentioned]  {I}", "metadata": "AG"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>The families belonging to this group were described in the Velvet Book and the pedigree</u></b></em> <em><b><u>books.</u></b></em><b><u> This group, which was a rank below the druzhina, benefited from the Mestnichestvo</u></b> <b><u>system. The power of this group was opposed by the creation of twelve collegia and by the</u></b> <b><u>formulation of civil service in the (+)</u> Table of Ranks. Members of this group made up a namesake</b> (*) Duma assembly, wore hats called gorlatnaya and carried silver tokens if they paid the beard tax. For 10 points, name this group targeted by Peter the Great's reforms, Russia's traditional nobility.", "answer": "<b><u>boyar</u></b>s [prompt on \"Russian nobles\" or similar answers]  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>This movement believed in a spiritual realm called the Pleroma.</u></b></em><b><u> Carl Jung wrote about</u></b> <b><u>this movement's \"Symbols of the Self.\" Many writings of this movement were discovered at</u></b> <b><u>Nag Hammadi, including the (+)</u>Gospel of Thomas. Its followers believed that the creator of the world was the Demiurge, who is typically depicted asa child of</b> (*) Sophia. For 10 points, what sets of early Christian heretics believed in the idea that one could attain salvation through knowledge, and took its name from the Greek for that type of knowledge?", "answer": "<b><u>Gnostic</u></b>ism [or <b><u>Gnostic</u></b>s]  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>A coup attempt against this dynasty resulted in the \"six martyred ministers\" being executed</u></b></em><b><u>.</u></b> <b><u>The fourth ruler of this dynasty created a set of scholarly advisors called the Hall of</u></b> <b><u>Worthies. This dynasty was the last under which civil servants called</u>(+) </b><em><b>yangban</b></em><b> had high social status. The European phrase \"hermit kingdom\" referred to this dynasty during its later isolationist years, after it developed the</b> (*) covered hulls of the turtle ship. For 10 points, name this dynasty whose emperor Sejong invented the <em>hangul</em> script, which ruled until 1910 on the Korean peninsula.", "answer": "<b><u>Choson</u></b> dynasty [or <b><u>Joseon</u></b> dynasty]  {I}", "metadata": "MJ"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Speaking tours for this cause were conducted by Hanley's Flying Squadron.</u></b></em><b><u> This</u></b> <b><u>movement was supported by a Timothy Shay Arthur novel describing \"Ten Nights in\" a</u></b> <b><u>certain place \"and What I Saw There.\" Wayne Wheeler and \"Pussy-foot\" Johnson (+)</u> founded a league for this cause. This cause was supported by the \"Maine Laws,\" which were advocated byPortland Mayor Neal S.</b> (*) Dow. The hatchet-wielding Carrie Nation supported this cause, as did the WCTU. For 10 points, name this cause which succeeded with the passage of the 18th Amendment and the prohibition of alcohol.", "answer": "<b><u>temperance</u></b> [or <b><u>prohibition</u></b> before read; or <b><u>Anti-Saloon</u></b> League]  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Three members of this group were shot in Gibraltar during Operation Flavius.</u></b></em><b><u> Imprisoned</u></b> <b><u>members of this group walked around naked and smeared feces in their cells as part of</u></b> <b><u>\"blanket\" and \"dirty\" protests against the removal of their Special Category Status. This</u></b> <b><u>group</u><u>blew up Lord</u> (+) Mountbatten's yacht and attempted a bombing of the Grand Hotel in Brighton. (*) </b>\"Continuity\" and \"Real\" offshoots of this group emerged after the Good Friday Agreement. For 10 points, name this paramilitary group active during the Troubles, which sought to create a united Ireland.", "answer": "Provisional <b><u>Irish Republican Army</u></b> [or <b><u>IRA</u></b>; or <b><u>PIRA</u></b>;do not accept other adjectives in front of the name]  {I}", "metadata": "JB"}, {"question": "<em><b><u>Sarah Josepha Hale advocated for the establishment of this holiday.</u></b></em><b><u> The day before this</u></b> <b><u>holiday, the</u> </b><em><b><u>Wall Street Journal</u></b></em><b><u> reprints a section of</u> </b><em><b><u>Mourt\u2019s Relation</u></b></em><b><u> known as \"The</u></b> <b><u>Desolate Wilderness.\" In 1939 the date of this holiday</u><u>was</u> (+) moved after lobbying from the National Retail Dry Goods Association. In 1864 Abraham Lincoln (*)</b> proclaimed it to be a national holiday. This holiday was first celebrated in a 1621 gathering legendarily aided by Squanto. For 10 points, a 1941 act of Congress proclaimed what holiday to be the fourth Thursday in November?", "answer": "<b><u>Thanksgiving</u></b> Day  {I}", "metadata": "DW"}], "bonuses": []}